{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "The heresy of Adoptionism was created by this city’s archbishop Elipandus. In one legend, this city’s Alcazar fortress refused to surrender, even after Jose Moscardo’s son was taken for ransom. This European city produced swords used by both Hannibal’s Carthaginians and the Roman legions; those swords were made of a steel alloy that was unmatched until the discovery of Damascus steel in the Middle Ages. For ten points, name this city in central Spain that was once called the “Imperial City” as the seat of Charles V’s court.",
      "answer": "Toledo"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to several European folklore traditions, the fossilized remains of belemnoids are formed by this phenomena. In Japanese mythology, a white skinned kami uses taiko drums to control this phenomenon. The power of this phenomenon and the durability of diamond are embodied by the vajra, a ritual weapon wielded by another god who is praised in the ancient hymns of the Rigveda for slaying Vritra. Raijin and Indra are gods of, for ten points, what meteorological phenomenon that is wielded as a weapon by Zeus?",
      "answer": [
        "lightning bolts",
        "thunderbolts"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This city’s government lost the Supreme Court case Ricci v. DeStefano against a group of firefighters who were not promoted despite passing qualification tests. In this city, James Hillhouse established the first public tree planting project in America, leading it to be nicknamed “The Elm City.” This city was the birthplace of a group known as “Order 322” or “Skull and Bones,” whose collegiate members included John Kerry and George W. Bush. For ten points, name this Connecticut city that is home to Yale University.",
      "answer": "New Haven"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ship was sent to patrol the Burdwood Bank on what would be its final mission. This ship was formally commissioned as the USS Phoenix, but was eventually sold off for the People’s Loyalty Day celebration. After this ship was sunk, The Sun published an infamous headline that read “Our lads sink gunboat and hole cruiser.” The “Gotcha!” headline trumpeted the sinking of this ship, the first ever to be sunk by a nuclear submarine. A general who fought for Argentine independence names, for ten points, what ship that was sunk during the Falklands War?",
      "answer": "ARA General Belgrano"
    },
    {
      "question": "An 1887 experiment involving a block of sandstone floating in mercury failed to find the fringe shift expected by a “wind” generated by this substance. This substance is supposed to be dragged by the Earth moving through it, a process not detected by the Michelson-Morley experiment. The theory of relativity was able to explain the non-existence of, for ten points, what hypothetical substance through which light moves, according to a theory that was finally debunked in the early 20th century?",
      "answer": "luminiferous aether"
    },
    {
      "question": "This battle began despite the peacemaking efforts of Marcus Ambustus; negotiations broke down when one side began to fight with Clusium. This battle’s result forced the losing side to recall Camillus from exile in Veii and appoint him dictator; Camillus eventually returned and forced the Senones back from the Capitoline Hill. The winning commander in this battle allegedly threw his sword on a scale after demanding 1,000 pounds of gold to be paid as ransom, declaring “woe to the vanquished.” For ten points, name this 390 BC battle that allowed Brennus to sack Rome.",
      "answer": "Battle of the Allia River"
    },
    {
      "question": "An opera titled for one of these people ends with a chorus singing “Glory, Glory to you.” One of these people falls in love with Marfa in a Rimski-Korsakov opera titled for one of these people’s Bride. The hero Susanin leads Poles into a blizzard in a Mikhail Glinka opera titled A Life for one of these people. The song “flow, flow bitter tears” ends a Modest Mussorgsky opera in which one of these leaders gives the throne to his son Fyodor. Boris Godunov held, for ten points, what position that was abolished with the fall of the Romanovs?",
      "answer": "tsar of Russia or czar of Russia"
    },
    {
      "question": "Asettlement known as Keshetwas createdon the grounds where this region’s primary city of Quneitra had been burned to the ground. The southern portion of Mount Hermon extends into this region, where the Purple Line was created after a ceasefire during the 1973 Yom Kippur War. In the aftermath of a 1967 war, over 100,000 refugees fled this region. For ten points, name this plateau region of the Levant that Israel captured from Syria during the Six Day War.",
      "answer": "Golan Heights"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was lampooned as an “anti-poverty czar” by Jack Anderson while Director of the Office of Economic Opportunity under Nixon. This man replaced James Schlesinger after the Halloween Massacre, becoming the youngest Secretary of Defense in U.S. history. This man’s visit with Saddam Hussein during the Reagan administration came under scrutiny during his later second term as Defense Secretary, when he oversaw the Abu Ghraib prison complex. For ten points, name this Secretary of Defense under George W. Bush who oversaw the wars in Afghanistan and Iraq.",
      "answer": "Donald Rumsfeld"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Body of Liberties was established as a legal code for this colony, which was bounded by the “Old Colony Line.” Midwife Margaret Jones was hanged in this colony after her patients got sicker. John Cotton was an early settler in this colony, the first American colony to legalize slavery. During the Antinomian Controversy, Anne Hutchinson was banished from this colony. Governor John Winthrop delivered the “City upon a hill” sermon in, for ten points, what English colony founded by Puritans that was centered on Salem and Boston?",
      "answer": "Massachusetts Bay Colony"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This group conspired with Amalric of Tyre to overthrow Henry II of Cyprus. This group was allowed to pay no taxes and travel freely across borders by Pope Innocent II’s papal bull Omne Datum Optimum, which may have been prompted by support from this group’s patron, Bernard of Clairvaux. This group relieved Baldwin IV’s forces at Montgisard. Members of this group were arrested for heresy by Philip IV, after which many joined the Knights Hospitaller. For ten points, name this chivalric order active in the crusades.",
        "answer": "Knights Templar"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Knights Templar were officially dissolved by this Pope, whose refusal to move to Rome ushered in the Avignon Papacy.",
        "answer": "Clement V"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In one speech, this man condemned a senator for taking “a mistress...polluted in the sight of the world;” after that speech, Laurence Keitt brandished a pistol to prevent a brawl from breaking out. This man used Don Quixote and Sancho Panza as comparisons for Andrew Butler and Stephen Douglas after they wrote an 1854 act. For ten points, name this Republican, a Massachusetts senator who gave “The Crime Against Kansas” speech and was caned by Preston Brooks.",
        "answer": "Charles Sumner"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "As chairman of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, Charles Sumner helped defuse this 1861 affair, which began after the U.S. Navy captured two Confederate ambassadors to the British.",
        "answer": "Trent affair"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Churches named for this commodity dotted East Anglia in England and were named due to the largest donations coming from rich local merchants. “Owlers” smuggled this good out of England. In 1378, workers of this industry fought to form a government of disenfranchised craftsmen in Florence after leading the Ciompi Rebellion. The Navigation Acts banned the American colonies from buying this textile commodity except from England. Mohair and angora are types of, for ten points, what textile that is most commonly sheared from sheep?",
        "answer": "wool"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the more notable Wool Churches is St. Agnes’ Church in this eastern English county, which shares its name with a Virginia city in the Hampton Roads region.",
        "answer": "Norfolk"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these events that affected the Selk’nam in the Tierra del Fuego was led by Romanian-Argentine engineer Julius Popper, who designed the city of Havana. Dmitry Milyutin carried out one of these events, forcing many Circassians to be quarantined in lazarettos in the Ottoman Empire. Lothar von Trotha committed one of these actions in Namibia after the Herero and the Nama rebelled against German rule, and another of these events occurred in modern Sudan in the Darfur region. For ten points, give this term for an atrocity against an entire racial group, such as the Holocaust.",
        "answer": "genocides"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Polish-Jewish lawyer coined the word genocide and described the Holodomor as “the destruction of the Ukrainian nation,” a “classic example of Soviet genocide”.",
        "answer": "Raphael Lemkin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2006, this man was ultimately convicted of insider trading in Soci´et´e G´en´erale, a French bank that he had invested in in 1988. This man made over a billion dollars on September 16, 1992, known as Black Wednesday, because this man held a ten billion dollar short position on the pound; as a result, he became known as “the man who broke the Bank of England.” Charter 77 and Solidarity were among the political groups funded by this man, who has been a common target of American right-wing pundits and anti-Semites. For ten points, name this Hungarian born founder of the philanthropic Open Society Foundations, a liberal activist and investor.",
        "answer": "George Soros"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Prime Minister of Malaysia blamed “a Jew” - implied to be Soros - for destroying his country’s economy in 1997.",
        "answer": "Mahathir bin Mohamad"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "William Gilpin was the first governor of this territory, where Lewis Ralston found gold at a creek now named for him. George Custer won the Battle of Washita River in this territory where, in 1864, volunteers under John Chivington massacred members of the Cheyenne and Arapaho tribes. President Grant made this territory a state in 1876. For ten points, name this territory to which the “Fifty-Niners” migrated during the Pike’s Peak Gold Rush.",
        "answer": "Colorado Territory"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "John Chivington’s men killed hundreds of Cheyenne and Arapaho people, mostly women and children, in this November 1864 massacre.",
        "answer": "Sand Creek Massacre"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A Washington, DC memorial to this event commemorates the deaths of Francis David Millet and Archibald Butt; William Howard Taft spoke at Butt’s funeral. Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney designed another memorial in Washington, D.C. that was “Erected by the Women of America” for the “Brave Men who Perished” in this event to “Save Women and Children.” Graves of unknown victims of this event in Halifax, Nova Scotia are marked with the date “15 April 1912” and were established through a trust from the White Star Line. For ten points, name this event in which over 1,500 people died after a collision with an iceberg.",
        "answer": "sinking of the RMS Titanic"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The musicians of the Titanic were honored with a memorial in Southampton that was destroyed by German bombers in 1940 and replaced in 1990. The memorial includes an inscription of the opening bars of this song, legendarily the last song played by the Titanic musicians as the ship sank.",
        "answer": "Nearer, My God, to Thee"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This object gained a nickname after a leader promised, “we’ll show you!” at a United Nations assembly, leading it to become known as “Kuzma’s mother.” A Tu-95V was equipped with reflective white paint to protect Andrei Durnovtsev during a test of this object, which built on the RDS-37 design. This object was tested at Severny Island in Novaya Zemlya, releasing 51 megatons of energy. For ten points, name this Soviet bomb, the strongest nuclear weapon ever detonated.",
        "answer": "Tsar Bomba"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The team that built Tsar Bomba included this Russian physicist who became a disarmament peace activist shortly thereafter. The European Parliament awards an annual prize for Freedom of Thought named after this man.",
        "answer": [
          "Andrei Sakharov",
          "Sakharov Prize"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Japanese-American Internment",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "War in which the United States started interning the Japanese-Americans after Pearl Harbor.",
          "answer": "World War II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Government program whose neighborhood-level data, collected every 10 years, was used to identify Japanese for internment.",
          "answer": "US Census Bureau"
        },
        {
          "question": "Large camp in California’s Owens Valley, the first to be constructed.",
          "answer": [
            "Manzanar War Relocation Center",
            "any additional information with Manzanar"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Executive order, issued by FDR, that implemented internment.",
          "answer": "Executive Order 9066"
        },
        {
          "question": "California politician, Attorney General until 1943 and Governor after, who publicly pushed for internment.",
          "answer": "Earl Warren"
        },
        {
          "question": "Activist who lost a 1944 Supreme Court case upholding the legality of the exclusion zones.",
          "answer": [
            "Fred Korematsu",
            "Korematsu v. US"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Justice who wrote the majority opinion of that case, holding that protection outweighed civil liberties.",
          "answer": "Hugo Black"
        },
        {
          "question": "General who oversaw the internment through his Military Proclamation Number 1, claiming it was merely an evacuation.",
          "answer": "John L. Dewitt"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "First Triumvirate",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Most politically connected member of the three, who was assassinated on the Ides of March.",
          "answer": "Gaius Julius Caesar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Richest of the three, who fought the Parthians in 53 BC.",
          "answer": "Marcus Licinius Crassus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Third member of the Triumvirate, known as “the Great,” who was beheaded after losing the Battle of Pharsalus.",
          "answer": [
            "Pompey the Great",
            "Gnaeus Pompeius Magnus"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Military celebration for performance in Hispania that was abandoned to allow one member to stand for consul.",
          "answer": "Caesar’s triumph"
        },
        {
          "question": "Woman, a daughter of one member married to another, whose death in childbirth in 54 BC darkened the alliance.",
          "answer": "Julia"
        },
        {
          "question": "53 BC battle where the first of the three to die was killed, officially ending the alliance.",
          "answer": "Battle of Carrhae"
        },
        {
          "question": "Populist who gave away grain to the poor during the Triumvirate and was murdered on the Appian Way in 52 BC.",
          "answer": "Publius Clodius Pulcher"
        },
        {
          "question": "Co-consul in 59 BC who had feces poured on him at the Temple of Castor and Pollux while opposing the Triumvirate on a bill.",
          "answer": "Marcus Calpurnius Bibulus"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Chinese Unrest",
      "prompt": "Name the Chinese rebellion that was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Supported by the Qing Dynasty, and was defeated by the western Eight-Nation Alliance in 1901.",
          "answer": [
            "Boxer Rebellion",
            "Yihetuan Movement"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Led by a supposed brother of Jesus named Hong Xiuquan and established a heavenly kingdom in Nanjing.",
          "answer": "Taiping Rebellion"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led by the Zhang family and which led to the Three Kingdoms period.",
          "answer": [
            "Yellow Turban Rebellion",
            "Yellow Scarves Rebellion"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Carried out by followers of a hybrid Buddhism movement, named for a flower.",
          "answer": "White Lotus Rebellion"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led by Zhang Lu, whose adherents had to donate food to enter; they surrendered to Cao Cao [sow sow] in 215 AD.",
          "answer": [
            "Way of the Celestial Masters",
            "Way of the Five Pecks of Rice",
            "Wu dou Mi Dao"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Led by Zhu Yuanzhang, who eventually named himself the Hongwu Emperor, against the Yuan.",
          "answer": [
            "Red Turban Rebellion",
            "Red Scarves Rebellion",
            "Hongjin Qiyi"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Sparked by the Wuchang Uprising; it ended imperial rule in China in 1911.",
          "answer": "Xinhai Revolution"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led by farmers against the Xin [shin] dynasty; it was named for its followers’ painting their faces to appear like demons.",
          "answer": [
            "Red Eyebrows",
            "Chimei"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This battle’s losing commander declared that “we are in the chamber pot” after falling into a trap near La Moncelle. A failed attempt to break out at Floing led to the death of Jean Margueritte during this battle. Officer casualties in this battle forced Auguste (20 pts)",
        "Ducrot to take command before he, too, was replaced by Emmanuel Wimpffen. This battle began when Patrice MacMahon attempted to lift the Siege of Metz, only to be surrounded. The (10 pts)",
        "Second French Empire fell after, for ten points, what battle of the Franco-Prussian War that led to the capture of Napoleon III?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Sedan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Octavio Paz invited this man to a 1990 conference where he cited the example of the PRI to claim that “Mexico is the perfect dictatorship.” As a FREDEMO party candidate, this man won the first round of a 1990 presidential election but lost the run-off to a dark horse candidate from the right-wing Cambio 90 ticket, (20 pts)",
        "Alberto Fujimori. The dictatorship of Manuel Odria is the setting of Conversation in the Cathedral, a (10 pts)",
        "novel by, for ten points, what Peruvian politician and author of Aunt Julia and the Scriptwriter who won the 2010 Nobel Prize in Literature?"
      ],
      "answer": "Mario Vargas Llosa"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Elizabeth Drinker unsuccessfully appealed to this woman in an attempt to free a group of Quaker soldiers who failed to give a loyalty oath. This woman’s marriage to Daniel Parke Custis ended with his death, leaving her with over 300 (20 pts)",
        "slaves and a massive estate at age 25. In 1777, this woman attended a production of the play Cato put on by soldiers at (10 pts)",
        "Valley Forge during a visit to meet her more famous second husband. For ten points, name this matriarch of Mount Vernon, the wife of George Washington."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Martha Washington",
        "Martha Dandridge",
        "Martha Custis before “Custis” is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The remains of dome shaped huts have been found on this island at Mount Sandel. Hundreds of wedge tombs, including the Hag’s Bed, were built facing the setting sun in the north of this island. This island’s Neolithic monument (20 pts)",
        "Newgrange features a burial chamber that lights up during the winter solstice; that monument is found just west of Drogheda [draw-duh] on the (10 pts)",
        "River Boyne. For ten points, name this European island that was settled by the Gaels before the 1169 Norman invasion from Britain to the east."
      ],
      "answer": "Ireland"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Among the thousands of birch bark manuscripts excavated in this city are homework assignments from a six-year-old named Onfim. A ruler of this city ascended to the throne after overthrowing his brother with the assistance of Sartaq Khan and the Golden Horde. This city was saved from a (20 pts)",
        "Swedish invasion by the victory of a teenage prince at the Battle of Neva. This city’s namesake republic was annexed by Muscovy under Ivan III. A prince of this city defeated the (10 pts)",
        "Teutonic Knights on the frozen Lake Peipus in the 1242 Battle of the Ice. For ten points, name this powerful medieval Russian city, the home of Alexander Nevsky."
      ],
      "answer": "Novgorod"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man starred as Genghis Khan in The Conqueror, a 1956 movie that was filmed downwind of nuclear testing grounds in Nevada; this man died of possibly-related stomach cancer in 1979. This man, who was nominated for an Oscar as a producer on a 1960 film about the (20 pts)",
        "Alamo, won his only Oscar in 1969 for playing Rooster Cogburn in (10 pts)",
        "True Grit. The Shootist, The Searchers, and Stagecoach are among the over 100 films to feature, for ten points, what American western film star?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "John Wayne",
        "Marion Morrison"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this battle, one side’s advances up Edson’s Ridge forced the other side to call up reinforcements from the Kokoda Track. Supplies in this battle were taken down “the slot” under a system known as the Tokyo Express. This battle was codenamed Operation (20 pts)",
        "Watchtower and featured the capture of Savo and Tulagi Islands. This battle was initiated to capture the airstrip at (10 pts)",
        "Henderson Field, which was to be used as a base for further attacks in the Pacific. For ten points, name this 1943 battle over a namesake island in the Solomons."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Guadalcanal"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader was supported by the British contingency plan Giralda, which would have prevented a coup attempt by the rival Umma party. Many of this leader’s reforms were undone by the “everything goes” policy of successor Ali Mwinyi. Following a dispute over his country’s (20 pts)",
        "Kagera region, this leader restored Milton Obote to power in Uganda over the defeated Idi Amin. This leader’s policy of (10 pts)",
        "ujamaa was outlined in his Arusha Declaration, a manifesto of African socialism. Zanzibar and Tanganyika were unified during the tenure of, for ten points, what first president of Tanzania?"
      ],
      "answer": "Julius Nyerere"
    }
  ]
}